hey there welcome to farm craft i've got
two chainsaw chains here
both of these have good properly
sharpened teeth they're both nice and
sharp
this one won't cut worth a darn this one
cuts great
at the end of this video you're going to
understand why i've watched a lot of the
videos that are on youtube about
sharpening chains
there's a couple things that they leave
out one in particular that is much more
likely to be a problem
for the non-professional sharpening a
chainsaw chain for a lot of hobbyists
and home gamers
is a bit of a mystery sometimes but it's
really not that hard you just have to
have some basic understanding
of how a chain works how it cuts and
then you know how to sharpen it and you
can you can make even an old
ragged out chain cut grate and i'm gonna
go through all of that in this video so
this is everything you need to know
on sharpening chainsaw chains there's
three things you need to do to sharpen a
chainsaw chain
no but seriously there really is three
things you need to do first
you need to get the teeth sharp so here
i've got my chainsaw grabbed in a vise
this is very helpful and this is how i
do it when i'm around the shop let's
take a close look at this chain here so
these are the teeth
that right there that right there that
right there
and that's what you need to sharpen the
chain goes this way
so the teeth are going back on the
bottom and you do most of your cutting
on the bottom but you can cut on either
side of the bar
now i want you to see these teeth in
action and uh doing this by hand i can't
do it on a piece of wood
but i think we can do it with this piece
of cheese this tooth here
is going to contact this cheese
and it cuts a chip off of it
like that and then the other side comes
and cuts a chip in the opposite
direction
and then this side again the other side
nothing like the taste of bar oil in the
morning
so doing the same thing with a piece of
wood you can see
how this riker tooth contacts the wood
and then the tooth comes and strikes the
wood and then of course
i'm not strong enough to rip that chip
out because this is a piece of wood it
would then
chisel a slot through there and then the
next tooth would come
the raker would hit and then it would
chisel
and it's on the opposite side so the two
teeth together make a trough
one does the right side one does the
left side so the big secret the best way
to sharpen is with
the humble hand file seriously this
really is the best you don't have to buy
some expensive grinder or jig
this is what you want if you own a
chainsaw do yourself a favor
and learn how to sharpen with a hand
file it's going to serve you very well
the reason is is because you need to
sharpen a chain often when you're out in
the woods cutting
it's guaranteed at some point you're
going to hit the dirt you're going to
hit a rock you're going to hit a piece
of metal in the wood that you're cutting
it's going to dull your chain and now
you're out in the woods with a dull
chain what do you do
well if you know how to hand file and
all you have with you is this
you're back up and cutting in just a few
minutes this is what the professionals
use
they use it multiple times a day one
rule of thumb is every time you have to
put gas in your saw
sharpen the chain a hand file can
actually do a better job than a grinder
the problem with grinders is they can
remove too much material
they can overheat the teeth they wear
your chain out faster
if you do a good job hand filing and
you're careful with your chain you can
sharpen a chain 10 times and it'll still
be cutting just like it was new
now a quality chainsaw is going to have
a mark on the tooth
and that is the angle at which you're
supposed to hold your file
so you want your file at that angle not
that
not that that and you know it doesn't
have to be perfect
but basically this is your your
sharpening motion
all right so i'm going to do all the
teeth on this side
first so that i don't have to keep
changing my grip i i line up the angle
i hold both ends of the file and give it
a good firm stroke
now i am pushing it kind of into the
tooth
so that i'm getting both that top edge
and the side edge this top edge here and
then this side edge here
and it should come to a nice point now
what i do
i just take the file against this uh
this raker tooth here
and i push to the next tooth with the
file so i don't have to touch the chain
with my hands
so this tooth it's not in bad shape but
you can see the top's a little irregular
now that top is nice and straight comes
to a nice point
good sharp tooth let's go to the next
one
yeah this one's pretty rough see how it
doesn't come to a point and that's it's
not even straight there
the top of that's really rounded off
there good looking tooth not rocket
science here you know
the angle is right there it doesn't have
to be absolutely perfect
if you're off a degree or two it's going
to cut just fine
you know you don't want to be way off
you don't want to be like this but
just follow the angle that's there and
it's going to do fine
now when you get all the way around and
it's time to do the other side it's the
same thing
you change your position change your
hands and then
you follow that tooth angle
just the same
so i should mention i haven't used this
chain in years because i hit something
with it so i'm really having to take a
lot off these teeth to get them back up
to par
typically when you're out on a daze
cutting and you just want to freshen up
your chain
three or four strokes is all you need to
do
uh
now for the other side i step over to
the left side
and i do the same thing and this is
where the vise
really makes you much more consistent
because i can
i can look right down that angle and
make sure that i'm keeping that file on
the angle
so you're out in the woods and you don't
have a vise set your saw down
straddle it pinch the front of it with
your knees
and i'm holding the back sort of with my
my calves
and file like this
and then the other way
now for us old-timers this is a little
harder on your back i wouldn't recommend
this doing on a real
beat-up chain because you'll be here a
while but when you're out in the woods
and you just need to touch up your chain
three strokes a tooth
you can knock it out pretty quick
another option is to buy a stump vise
which is a little clamp that you pound
into a stump that allows you to grab the
bar and still be able to move the chain
so that's how you sharpen a single tooth
now the issue is
all the teeth need to be the same length
they don't have to be perfect you don't
have to get out calipers and measure
each tooth
but this tooth i can kind of look at it
and you know what is the distance from
from this angle line here to the edge of
the tooth
and i get a feel for that distance and
let me show you
let's see here that tooth is
significantly longer
so i need to take off of this tooth to
about there
and that's going to include the other
side now this tooth is about the right
length
and doesn't look to be in bad shape so i
won't have to sharpen that one a whole
lot
that one will need some this one will
need less can you see that that tooth
is a little longer than that tooth and
just in case people aren't aware what
i'm talking about with the length of the
teeth
so this is a brand new chain right here
and this is a chain that's most of the
way through its service life and we'll
see the length from here to there
versus from here to there see how much
shorter that tooth has gotten with
repeated sharpenings
let me show you one that's shot
that one is done those teeth are just
nubs you could make this cut
but it's just not worth your time at
that point if your chain is not marked
with the angles or you prefer to use one
of these
these file guides some people like them
it's just your file and it's just
clipped with this uh with this guide on
it
and this guide has various angles just
check what angle you're supposed to use
on your chain this one's 30 degrees
so i can see the 30 degree mark there i
just make it
parallel with the bar and
then run the file at that angle
so what i don't like about these is that
they cover up the tooth i can't see the
progress that i'm making i can't see the
tooth length while i'm doing it
this does do one thing though that's
really good for for beginners
is it gets the right amount of hook it
holds the file
at the proper height to the tooth
because
if you're inexperienced you may take
this file
and you may push down too much and
you'll drive down into the gullet
too much or you won't do it enough and
you'll
the file will be kind of coming up out
of the tooth and then you don't have
enough hook
and it won't cut right so this will keep
you
at the right elevation with the file as
well as the right angle
so if you're just starting out and
you're not having great luck
give one of these a try so what happens
if you have where
the teeth are all longer on one side
than the other side
well it's not going to cut it's going to
try to curve in the wood because the bar
is flat it's going to bind and it's not
going to it'll cut a little bit
but it's not going to cut deep into a
log reason for that is
these teeth are at an angle so that
is not flat it's go it's like an uphill
slant there
and this one also it's on an uphill
slant so as you
shorten this tooth you are also lowering
the tooth and if one side is longer than
the other then what you have is
one the long side wants to cut the short
side
is not cutting because this is already
cut deeper than this can reach
so they have to be the same length not
perfect you don't have to get calipers
eyeballing it works and it works well
and that brings us to step two you have
to adjust the depth of your rakers
this is called a raker the raker height
relative to the tooth height
is what determines the depth of the cut
so look at this raker right here
when i hold that flat file across
there's barely a gap underneath
and that is what determines the height
of your cut the more you take these
teeth down the more you're going to have
to file the top of that off
so that you're not just making little
tiny sawdust chips
and making real chips for most chains
the depth is supposed to be
25 thousandths point six millimeters
now they sell
depth gauges like this that you hold
across your teeth
and then it gives you the proper depth
right there you feel and see if your
tooth is
too high or not and if it's high you
file some off
i don't use these this is a lousy one
i'm going to show a picture of a
of a much better type of depth gauge if
you want to use one
here this type protects your freshly
sharpened cutting teeth
and makes this process a lot easier so
there's a debate on if these are called
rakers or depth gauges
for those of you who prefer to call them
depth gauges what do you call this tool
a depth gauge
gauge
so this part is really easy and fast but
absolutely necessary if you want your
chain to cut right
so i need to take a little bit off of
these and it's better to file
from one side you'll see what i mean if
you go the wrong way it wants to chatter
but if you go from the right side it'll
make a nice cut and a little
a little goes a long way on this you
know a swipe or two is all you need
i like to kind of push away from my
freshly sharpened tooth
and that's it that just gave me
additional depth to all my cuts
some people when they do this they don't
like the flat spot on top of the tooth
and they want to round it off
i've never found that necessary you know
you can do that i don't
i don't think it makes any difference
the chain cuts just fine either way
i actually like to get a feel for my saw
and its power and how aggressive i like
it to cut
i take a little more off the rakers than
most do which makes it cut faster
it also makes kickbacks and stuff like
that are going to be more powerful
because the teeth dig in more
for a beginner who's not really used to
using a chainsaw
keep these light keep it cutting small
chips and the the chain's not going to
be so aggressive and so grabby on the
wood
i should mention when doing your depth
if you have a less powerful saw
and the chain is stalling all the time
it's grabbing in the wood and it won't
keep turning
your depth is set too deep so you need
to back off on that so that
the saw has enough power to power
through so there we go we've sharpened
all our teeth
they're all the same length we've got
the depth set right
but your saw still not cutting right now
what
the next thing we need to do is step
three which is check your bar
if you want to rotate your bar up and
down there's no even though the
writing's one way there's no up or down
on these you're gonna wear out
only one side if you always keep that
writing face up so
rotate it periodically but as you're
cutting and especially when you're
cutting with a with a chain that maybe
isn't so sharp
you're pushing the equipment hard this
bar is going to get hot
and when it gets hot it's going to start
to roll over and you'll get a burr right
there
and i actually have a little bit of a
burr there
see right there on the edge of the bar
a burr has rolled over it should be
perfectly flat
when that burr gets big enough as you're
going down through the log a piece of
wood
will catch on that burr and it will hang
it up and the saw won't be cutting and
you'll wonder why and it's not the teeth
it's because a little fiber of wood
keeps lodging on the edge of this bur
this is an easy problem to solve and
just takes a minute
feel the edge of that take your file
and just knock it off until there's no
burr left
there now that's nice and smooth there's
nothing to hang up as that bar is going
through the wood
and you want to do that on all basically
four edges this side
this side and then flip it over and do
those sides too
the other thing to check with your bar
is is it straight if your bar is bent or
twisted
it is not going to cut right now you
could try straightening it out but
most likely you're just going to need to
get a new one so that's it that's step
three check out the bar make sure it's
not bent twisted
make sure it hasn't built up burrs on
the edge here beyond that there's no
reason your chainsaw won't cut and won't
cut great
all right so here's a little quiz this
is the chain that we looked at at the
beginning
and this is the one that i said had good
sharp teeth but won't cut right
so take a look at that and see if you
can see what the problem is
let me show you the top of it as well
there you can see the red where i mark
it that way i don't sharpen the same
tooth twice when i'm going around
you can see that this tooth is just
touching this line
and the raker is too but this one's
touching and this one's touching so the
rakers are just as high as the teeth on
this
so this chain is not going to cut well
at all
uh it's just going to be making dust
because these rakers are sticking up and
blocking the tooth from engaging the
wood
so that that's the problem with this
chain all right so take a look at this
chain i've got it lined up on the line
let me tip that towards you so you get a
good view
now this has a two-part raker that is uh
that's what's
on a safety chain and that helps reduce
kick back
but most of the chains i use are not
this type
let me show you the top of the chain
so what's wrong with this chain
the answer on this one is the teeth are
filed
incorrectly all of the right-handed
teeth are short
the left-handed teeth are longer so
short
long short long short long
short long and that
is not going to cut right that is going
to
cut on this side of the groove and not
on the other side of the groove and try
to make the bar
curve and then it will bind so here's
another chain
get a look at that what's wrong with
this chain
this one is totally worn out there's
hardly any teeth left
this is probably a little bit beyond
needing to be retired
and a couple other things i'll quickly
mention uh you can put a chain on
backwards
only an idiot would ever do it you know
i i certainly never have
no no never you throw a chain on and
your chain is not cutting it off you
might want to just take a look at that
make sure the teeth
on the top of the bar are facing that
way
another thing i want to show you is the
oiler on your bar
your bar's going on this way facing
toward the saw
at the top there's going to be a little
hole
right there is a little hole and that
can get plugged with sawdust well that's
where the oil comes into the bar and
lubricates your chain
so if your chain's getting really hot
it's getting dull very quickly it's
smoking
it may be that this is clogged so you
can blow that out with some compressed
air or just poke it out with a pin
or something if you use the other side
of the bar it's going to be right there
i hope you guys learned something in
this video useful to you if you did
consider subscribing and sharing the
video with your friends and on your
social media that's always appreciated
we'll see you guys on the next one and
happy cutting
[Music]
[Applause]
so
[Music]
you